<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A friendly call, or, A seasonable perswasive to unity directed to all nonconformists and dissenters in religion from the Church of England, as the only secure means to frustrate and prevent all popish plots and designs against the peace of this kingdom both in church and state / by a lover of the truth and a friend to peace and unity.</title>
            <author>Allen, William, d. 1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23665</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1064</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10550</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12714234</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12714234</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66156</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23665)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66156)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 372:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A friendly call, or, A seasonable perswasive to unity directed to all nonconformists and dissenters in religion from the Church of England, as the only secure means to frustrate and prevent all popish plots and designs against the peace of this kingdom both in church and state / by a lover of the truth and a friend to peace and unity.</title>
                  <author>Allen, William, d. 1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 66 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T. Basset and J. Leigh ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to William Allen.  Cf. Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian union --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Monica Tsuneishi</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:66156:1"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Carolus Alſton R. P. D. Hen. Epiſc. Lond. à ſacris domeſticis.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66156:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Friendly Call, OR A SEASONABLE PERSWASIVE TO UNITY. DIRECTED To all Nonconformiſts and Diſſenters in Religion from the Church of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi> As the only ſecure Means to Fruſtrate and Prevent all POPISH PLOTS and Deſigns againſt the Peace of this Kingdom both in <hi>CH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RCH</hi> and <hi>STATE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a Lover of the Truth and a Friend to <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pfal. 123.1.</hi>
                  </bibl> Behold how good and how pleaſant a thing it is, for Brethren to dwell together in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 Cor. 1.10.</hi>
                  </bibl> Now I beſeech you Brethren, by the Name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that ye all ſpeak the ſame Thing, and that there be no Diviſions among you; but that ye be perfectly joyned together, in the ſame Mind, and in the ſame Judgment.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Baſſet</hi> and <hi>J. Leigh</hi> Book<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:66156:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66156:2"/>
            <head>A Friendly Call, OR A PERSWASIVE TO UNITY.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE wiſeſt of Kings hath told us, that <hi>there is a Time, and ſeaſon for all things;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 3.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 7.</note> a <hi>Time to keep Silence, and a Time to Speak;</hi> and certainly now, if ever, the laſt Time is not only Convenient, but abſolutely Neceſſary: and ſhould Man hold his Peace, and neglect this Duty,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.11.</note> even <hi>the Stone ſhould cry out of the Wall, and the Beam of the Timber ſhall anſwer it.</hi> I could wiſh I had the Voyce of <hi>Sten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> that I might be heard throughout our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or that of a Trumpet, that I might be heard by the Ears of the People: I would cry aloud to this deaf
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:66156:3"/>Generation, that they might be awakened out of the dream they now ſeem to be poſſeſſed with, and be rouſed from the Lethargie and Apoplectical eſtate they now lye under.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 58.1</note> 
               <hi>Cry aloud, ſpare not, lift up thy Voice like a Trumpet, and ſhew my People their Treanſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and the Houſe of</hi> Jacob <hi>their Sins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I direct this my Diſcourſe and Friendly Call to all in General; but more particularly to thoſe, who are Diſſenters from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and who ſeem to make a breach in the Conformity, and happy Unity of the Church, and who through over-nice Scruples, cauſe a Schiſm and Rent in its ſeamleſs Garment. 'Tis to You that I now ſpeak, as a Friend, as a Brother, for ſo we ought to be one to another, and not as Wolves and Dogs, ſnarling and ſnapping one at the other, but with gentleneſs and freedom admoniſh one another:
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>With all lowlineſs and meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with long-ſuffering, forbearing one another in Love: Endeavouring to keep the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit, in the Bond of Peace.</hi> 'Tis the Command of <hi>Christ,</hi> who is Love it ſelf,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 13.34.</note> 
               <hi>that we Love one another:</hi> by it we are known to be his true Diſciples and followers of Him. And there can be no greater ſign of this Love, than Friendly to admoniſh one another of Errors, and ſtraying from the Truth; and to aſſiſt the weak, to raiſe up thoſe that fall; to call to Unity and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and to ſtir up to Peace and Amity: <hi>That we may be all of one Mind,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>having Compaſſion one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, loving as Brethren, being Pittiful, being Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, not rendring Evil for Evil, and Railing for Rail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:66156:3"/>
            <p>'Tis with this Spirit of Brotherly Love, and of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Friendſhip, that I would Call unto you at this Time, and though I would Call and Cry aloud, to be heard, and that I might unſtop your ſealed Ears, yet I would not do it in the Thunder and Ratle of Words only; in the empty noiſe of Sounds and gingling of Syllables; with vain Rhetorick or fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Oratory; but I would ſpeak home to your Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, to your Hearts, and to your Spirits; I would ſpeak Life and Fire, that you might be at this time Quickned, and that you might feel and be ſenſible of the Truth. I know, there have been many <hi>Boanerges,</hi> Sons of Thunder, that have rent the Mountains, and broken to peices the Rocks of Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with their Voices and with the Wind of their Mouths: there have been alſo thoſe who have made Earth-quakes, and troubled the waters of Diſſention: there have been others, who with their fiery Zeal have burnt up all before them; and with too much Wrath, and Bitterneſs, have rather widened than healed up the Breaches; and by ſuch Debates and Diſputes have rather hindred than farthered the happy and deſired Unity and Conformity in the Land. I will not ſay God was not in them, but I would now with a ſtill ſmall Voice ſpeak Peace and Harmony, perſwade to Unity and Conformity, to Brotherly Love and Affection; I would ſpeak with the Tongue of Charity rather than with that of Men and Angels; I would bring Balm to your Wounds and Eaſe to your Griefs of Separation: This is the End, this is the Scope, and this is the meaning and true intention of this Call at this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66156:4"/>time:
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.11</note> 
               <hi>that we may be of good Comfort, and of one Mind, that we may live in Peace, and that the God of Love and Peace may be with us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the intention of this Call is Charity to the whole Nation, I come not therefore with Launcets and Razers, to cut and break up the Wounds, or with Probes and Pledgets, to ſearch or keep them open; the Wounds of Diviſion and Separation have been ſufficiently handled by able and skilful Chirurgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and now is the time, if ever, to apply a Cataplaſm, and healing Plaiſter, a ripening and cicatricing Seare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, that there may no Scar or Deformity remain, which <hi>Panacea</hi> is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Spirit in the bond of Peace.</hi> And as this is it I would Call to in Charity and with all earneſtneſs, with Love and alſo with Power, ſo I would do it in few Words, and if I could, to the purpoſe.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 6.7. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14 19</note> For it was a Heatheniſh fault, to <hi>uſe vain repetition, and to be thought to be heard for much Speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> and I had, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſays, much rather ſpeak <hi>five words with my understanding, that I might be bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial to others, than ten thouſand not to be understood;</hi> therefore as the Wiſe-Man Counſels,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.19.</note> 
               <hi>My Words ſhall be few, for in the multiplicity thereof there wanteth not Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now in the firſt place Conſider, that <hi>Love</hi> is the ſpecial Command of Jeſus Chriſt our Pattern, by whoſe Name we are Called, our Saviour and our Maſter; 'tis a Mark by which he will have his true Sheep known from the counterfeit, from the Wolves in Sheeps cloathing;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>John</hi> 4.20.</note> and St. <hi>John</hi> will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve any one, that ſhall make a Profeſſion of Love to God, and not at the ſame time ſhew it to his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:66156:4"/>he tells him, that ſhall ſo Profeſs, that <hi>he is a Lyar:</hi> and ſurely 'tis the greateſt Hypocriſie in the World, and we deceive our ſelves, if we think we can at any time truly Love God, whilſt at the ſame time we are at open Enmity and Hatred with our Brother.</p>
            <p>But let us not commit a great Miſtake, and think they only to be our Brethren, that are of our own Way, our own Profeſſion, our own Church-fellowſhip, and Brother-hood; and that Chriſt has reſtrained our Love to be extended only to the Few: who are then the Brethren? Chriſt tells you, <hi>one another;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.18. <hi>James</hi> 2.8 9</note> who are they? Your Neighbour whom you ought to Love as your Self, by which we fulfil the Royal Law, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Scripture; without reſpect of Perſons, for that is Sinful. Chriſt tells you this Neighbour is a <hi>Samaritan,</hi> a Separatiſt, one with whom the <hi>Jews</hi> had no Commerce, one of a different Judgment and profeſſion; a Sectary, a Diſſenter in Religion, a Nonconformiſt to the Worſhip at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> he that ſheweth Mercy and lives in Brotherly Love is this Neighbour: But <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath ſublimed this Royal Law of Love, and gone a ſtep beyond <hi>Moſes,</hi> that we might not miſtake and contract this Virtue, that is of ſo diffuſive and expanding a Nature, that can cover multitudes of faults, and extend it ſelf to all Mankind, and ſtretch its ample Wings over the whole World; <hi>Chriſt,</hi> I ſay, thinks it exceeds not the Love of <hi>Publicans</hi> to Love only good <hi>Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,</hi> ſuch as relieve your Wants, or uſe you Kindly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.46.</note> ſuch as Comply with you, ſuch as return you Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for Kindneſs, ſuch as walk Friendly with you;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66156:5"/>but he gives us a more general Command, that we may make no miſtakes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.44.</note> 
               <hi>Love your Enemies:</hi> thoſe that openly Profeſs themſelves Diſſenters, and that ſpeak evil of your way, and deſpitefully uſe you. Though there may be a difference between the Love ſhown to an Enemy and that towards a Brother, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more general, this being more near and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. But to Conclude, this love to the Brethren is ſo extenſive, that it ought to reach to all who make an open Profeſſion of the Name of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who confeſs him to be the Son of God and that he is come in the Fleſh; and who ſo ever truly Believeth this, is born of God, is thy Brother, and ought to be Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved;
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.1.</note> 
               <hi>for every one that loveth him that begat, loveth him alſo that is begotten of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since then 'tis ſo abſolutely neceſſary to keep this Royal Law of Love, if we will be true Chriſtians, and followers of Chriſt, there can be no greater Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to perſwade to Unity, as the means to that End; for without Unity we cannot conveniently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe this Brotherly Love; and without Concord and Agreement there can be no true Harmony; and whilſt there is a Separation and Diſagreement, Love is apt to wax cold; and Envyings, Backbitings, Hatred and Malice are apt to ariſe; Diſputes, Cavillings, Janglings and Debates are multiplied; which being all contrary to the Nature of Love and Peace, they are ſtifled and born down, and trampled under Foot: And thus the ſeamleſs Garment of the Church is torn in pieces, and the beauty of Unity ſpoiled. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>I beſeech you Brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10.</note> 
               <hi>by the Name of our Lord</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>that ye all ſpeak the ſame thing, and that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66156:5"/>there be no Diviſions among you, but that you be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly joyned together in the ſame Mind, and in the ſame Judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Diviſions and Schiſms, Rents and Separations, have ſprung up in the Church from the evil Seed of the wicked Sower, which have yielded an ample Crop of Tares, Cockle and Darnel. But it was not ſo at the firſt, <hi>Christ</hi> founded his Church upon the Rock of Unity, it was once Intire and Uniform; and the Apoſtles, and the Primitive Fathers of the Church built up the Superſtructure in Uniformity and with Intireneſs. There were no gaps ſeen in the Walls, there were no blemiſhes; the Stones ſtood not at a diſtance from one another, but cloſely united and cemented, and there appeared nothing but Beauty and Conformity. The Law of Love was exerciſed, there were no Names of Difference and Separation, no Names of Scorn and Infamy, they were diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by the Titles of Fathers, Sons and Brethren; and there was then in thoſe Happy and Golden days of the Church, though troubled by Perſecution, a true and perfect Concord, Harmony and Agreement. If there were any differences aroſe, they were ended without Strife, and without Diviſion and Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; though ſome were of <hi>Paul,</hi> and others of <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los,</hi> all were of God, in the Unity of Faith and in the Bond of Peace.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 85.10</note> 
               <hi>Then Mercy and Truth did meet together, and Righteouſneſs and Peace did kiſs each other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Evil one, who envies at the Unity of the Church of Chriſt, who cannot endure to behold its Glory and Conformity, who hates the Love of Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66156:6"/>who makes uſe of all his Cunning and Malice, to cauſe Diviſions and Separations; who ſowes En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyings, who plants Cavillings, who raiſes vain Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes, and frivolous Debates, and ſcatters up and down, idle and needleſs Scruples, to diſturb the quiet and the peace of the Church; who ſtill loves to Fiſh in troubled Waters; ſeeing the Beauty and Glory of United Chriſtians, made uſe of all his cunning Arts and Skill, and ſet to work all his evil Agents and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, to break this Unity, to ſow Diſcords and Diviſions, and to ſpoil the pleaſant Harmony of the People of God. All the Perſecutions that the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſtir'd up againſt the Saints, the many Deaths of the Martyrs, Afflictions, Croſſes, Diſgraces, Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, could not ſo well effect his deſires: he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that the Blood of the Martyrs was the <hi>ſemen Eccleſiae,</hi> that made the Church to flouriſh and ſpring up; he therefore flings away the Sword, and betakes himſelf to Poyſon, wherewith he more eaſily brought his Evil purpoſes and deſigns to paſs, and ſoon defaced the Beauty and Comelineſs of the Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church: the Poyſon of Pride, of Ambition, of Luxury and Eaſe, and of falſe Doctrine. By this means he ſet them at Variance one with another, the Children againſt the Father, the Father againſt the Children; the Shepherd againſt the Sheep, and the Sheep againſt the Shepherd; and the Paſtors againſt one another; the Flocks are ſcatter'd upon the Hills, and the fair Unity is broken. Thus a gap being made, how many Evils ſoon entred at theſe breaches? Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently Hereſies ſprung up, Sects increaſed, Schiſms multiplied, names of Diviſion and Separations were
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66156:6"/>known, then came into the World the ſpawns of <hi>Symonaicks, Nicholaitans, Cerinthians, Marcioniſts, Montanists, Porphyrians, Manachees, Novatians, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, Eunomians, Denatiſts, Photinians, Luciferians, Jovianists, Pelagians, Anthropomorphites, Nestorians, Sabbatians, Quaternians, Monothelites, Millenarians, Anabaptiſts, Socinians, Antinomians, Quakers,</hi> and many others; which multiplied like the <hi>Grecian</hi> Gods, of which <hi>Heſiod</hi> reckons up Thirty thouſand. Then every one ran after his own Inventions, they frame to themſelves Idols of their own; every Man will have an Ephod, a Church, a Congregation by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; all Government, all Obedience to Laws and Conſtitutions, all Submiſſion to Magiſtrates, to Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and Fathers of the Church are lay'd aſide, and every one does what ſeems good in his own Eyes; and thus Confuſion, Separation, Schiſm, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie and Rebellion were let in, to diſturb the Peace, the Quiet, and the Unity of the Church. Thus, I ſay, it was effected by the means of <hi>Satan,</hi> that Evil one, who ſtill makes it his great buſineſs, where ever he finds Unity and Peace, to ſpoil and deface them, and to raiſe up Strife and Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Since Separation and Diviſion among Brethren, proceeds from the Cunning and Malice of <hi>Satan,</hi> why ſhould it continue any longer in our <hi>Iſrael?</hi> Why ſhould not every Man put to his helping hand, to build up the Walls of Unity? Are we not Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren? Have we not one Father God? One Head <hi>Jeſus Chriſt?</hi> Is he not our Common Shepherd? Have we not one Faith, Salvation by Chriſt? Do
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66156:7"/>not we Believe him come in the Fleſh? Do not we Confeſs his Name? Are we not all Chriſtians? And indeed are we not alſo of one Mother the Church? Why then this Separation? This Diviſion? This drawing ſeveral Ways? Why cannot or why do not you Unite as you ought to do? If there be any ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacles and ſtumbling blocks of offence that lie in the way, ſet to your Hands and endeavor to remove them. I ſuppoſe they are not ſo many, nor ſo great, but they may be eaſily enough removed, if you go about it willingly and ſincerely; if you are not byaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or perverted by your own Paſſions and your own contradictory and perverſe Wills: if you are not Stubborn and Dogmatical, and not too ſtiff in your own Opinions in ſmall matters, you muſt yeild ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what in Love one to another, that the Work may be done and the Breaches made up; and that the Walls of a perfect Uniformity may at laſt be built for the ſecurity and welfare both of Church and State.</p>
            <p>And that this may be Effected and that our happy Unity may be laſting and perpetual, that the Stones may be made ſmooth and poliſhed fit for the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that they may lye faſt, equal and cloſe; all rug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedneſs and gratings muſt be done away, for whilſt they remain they will not be fit for the building, and there will be but little hopes of Conformity and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tireneſs. You muſt then lay aſide that bitterneſs of Spirit, which ſome of you call Zeal, wherewith you upbraid thoſe of the contrary Party, and to the multitude cunningly inſinuate an Opinion of Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Integrity of your Selves, and of looſneſs and neglect of your Adverſaries: always on the leaſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66156:7"/>occaſions laſhing them with ſharp and ſevere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs, ripping up the faults of Biſhops and the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of the Prelatical Party. You muſt leave theſe common Aſperſions which abound among many, throwing all Faults and Errors on the Eccleſiaſtical Government; and to it impute all Faults, all Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, endeavoring thereby to win to your ſelves the Opinion of Wiſdom: you muſt alſo leave to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude upon the People and your Hearers your own Form of Church Government, as the only remedy to avoid all Evils, as the only true Way to walk in, and as if Salvation were hard to be purchaſed any where elſe; and giving it ſo many glorious Titles and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comiums, and ſo poſſeſſing the minds of Men with an overweaning of the one, and a bitter and malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Scorn and Deteſtation of the other. Leave alſo to interpret the whole ſcope of Scripture, as if fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to maintain your own Form of Government, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting your Followers with falſe Gloſſes, whereby they read only as you would have them, and pervert Scripture to maintain the falſe Ideas of their ſickly Imaginations; and thus every Sect makes the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to ſpeak in favour of their Way and falſe Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to maintain their Schiſm and Separation; calling all <hi>Samaria</hi> and <hi>Babylon</hi> that are not of themſelves, and their own Congregations <hi>Sion</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> You muſt alſo leave off thoſe Names of Separation and Diſtinguiſhment, calling your ſelves the Godly, the Brethren, the Good People, Gods Children, the Sanctified; and others, the Ungodly, Reprobates, Worldlings, Time-ſervers, Men-pleaſers, Moraliſts, and <hi>Latitudinarians, Arminians,</hi> and the like. You
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66156:8"/>muſt alſo lay aſide that eager endeavor of making Proſelytes, eſpecially of the weaker Veſſels who are apt to be eaſily led and perſwaded by godly and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious pretences, though thereby they do great damage to their Husbands and Families, making the Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion within their private Walls as wide as that which you have cauſed in the Nation. You muſt alſo ceaſe to cry out and exclaim againſt Magiſtrates and Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, Kings and Governors, as Severe, Cruel and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical, upon the leaſt reſtraint of your Liberties; as if you were thereby become Martyrs for the Cauſe of Chriſt, and branding thoſe, that perhaps not with out occaſion given thereto, put ſome moderate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint upon you, with the Titles of Blood-ſuckers, and Blood-thirſty Men, Perſecutors and Tormentors; drawing all the Scriptures that any way favour the Innocency of ſuch as have Suffered for the Truth by wicked Tyrants, to your own ſelves, and apply them ſtill to your Caſe as if you were the Perſons pointed out by the Finger of the Holy Ghoſt, and for whom they were chiefly intended. Alſo you muſt not ſpeak contemptibly of Biſhops as you too frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly do, giving them ſcurrilous Names, as Limbs of Antichriſt, Locuſts of the bottomleſs pit, domineer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lords, Uſurpers, Spiritual Tyrants, Lordly Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, &amp;c. and calling the Miniſters of the Goſpel in contempt Prieſts, nay <hi>Baal</hi>'s Prieſts, Time-ſervers, Hirelings, State Divines, dumb Dogs, vain Bablers, with ſuch like Language; thoſe whom the Scriptures Dignifie and Honour with the Titles of Chriſts Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors, Gods Stewards, Paſtors of Chriſts flock, Stars, Angels, Gods, receive too often from you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66156:8"/>contrary Denominations; being ſcandalized at the Title of Lord given to Biſhops, which is an Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary Name annexed to their Temporalties by the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> you call them in Diſdain, Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, Proud, Imperious, Arrogant, and the like. You muſt alſo leave to Whiſper in private againſt the Governors and againſt the Secular Power, as if tending to and infected with Popery, and of complaining to your Diſciples that you are fain to fly to Corners and to Private Meetings, like the Primitive Chriſtians, whilſt Papiſts, Drunkards and Swearers are not medled with or diſturbed; that you are more roughly handled than thoſe who go to Maſs, that your Godly Meetings are diſturbed, whilſt Taverns, Ale-houſes and Play-houſes are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver look'd into, and where they commit Enormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties without Check or Controle: that you are the true Church, and that the Word and Sacraments are by you diſpenſed in Purity, and according to the Primitive Inſtitution; that the publick Places of Gods Worſhip are defiled with Common Prayers, Singing, Anthems, Read-Sermons and Set-Prayers, Organs, and ſuch like (as you call them) Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious rags of Popery. You muſt alſo utterly lay aſide all your Reverend thoughts of your great Idol the Covenant, the <hi>Moloch</hi> of Preſbytery, the <hi>Scottiſh Dagon,</hi> a very Monſter of Rebellion; this muſt be never thought of more, but laid aſide and drowned in the Sea of Oblivion. You muſt alſo leave off your continual Scoffing at the publick Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Church which you have termed Porridg, your unſeaſonable jeſts and jears againſt ſo Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66156:9"/>an exerciſe; compoſed by the moſt Learned and Holy Men of this Nation, and ſealed to with their Blood and Lives. And you muſt utterly diſclaim and remove out of the way, the very thoughts of that Principle that have been owned by you, and is a a very Mountain in the gap of Separation, that in the Cauſe of Religion it is Lawful to take up Arms againſt your King and Soveraign. You muſt alſo lay aſide that evil Eye which you have againſt the Riches and Revenues of the Biſhops, which you would gladly ſhare among your ſelves and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it no Sacriledge: The Biſhops Lands ſtick in your Stomachs, becauſe they have ſlipt from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween your Fingers; but be not your Eye evil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that of your Anceſtors has been good; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Pious Princes and Religious Nobles have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed ſo much means on the Church. They rob you not, 'tis not the effect of your Labour nor pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from the ſweat of your Brows, a Poor Clergy would be ſoon Vile and Contemptible. And though it be no fault to have a ſteady and unchanged Mind and Opinion upon well grounded Principles, yet I think all theſe ſtumbling blocks of Offences will not be accounted by your ſelves any found Principles or Foundations to build upon; but are Stones and Rocks againſt which you daſh your Feet, and which divert you from the path that leads to Peace and Unity: therefore be not over ſtiff in your own Opinions, and think it no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace or undervaluing to your Cauſe or Reputation to give way, and at laſt ſee the great Benefit that will accrue not only to the whole Nation but your
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66156:9"/>Selves, by putting to your own Hands to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving all theſe forementioned Obſtacles.</p>
            <p>I am not Ignorant that againſt this my Advice you have Objected the tenderneſs of your Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that has enfeebled your Hands and kept you back from performing what is required of you. But have a care you delude not your ſelves in this Point, and pretend Conſcience when there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe in the way. There is no Sect, no Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, the very Levellers and Ranters themſelves, but have the ſame Plea, and fly away from their Duties to this ſtarting hole. Conſcience hath been the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral pretence for all thoſe who had no mind to obey: 'Tis the common Shield and Buckler of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, but I think there can be no Plea for Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence when a lawful Authority requires only lawful things; ſuch as are not Derogatory to the Honor of God, nor hurtful to the common Society of Men. I know alſo that you will tell me,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.33.14.</note> that <hi>what is not of Faith is Sin,</hi> and that, though <hi>there is nothing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean of it ſelf;</hi> yet <hi>to him that eſteemeth any thing to be unclean, to him it is unclean.</hi> But have a care that your Conſcience, that is ſo tender, does not ſtrain at a Gnat and ſwallow a Camel, ſtumble at a Straw and leap over a Block: I would not have you to do any thing againſt Conſcience, but then you muſt rectifie your Conſcience by the Rule of Gods Word, otherwiſe it is no Conſcience; for there can be no pretence of Conſcience in doing Evil or Unlawful things, it muſt be only in indifferent things where it hangs <hi>in aequilibrio</hi> as it were, that it can admit of Doubts and Scruples. Known Good
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66156:10"/>and known Evil does not admit of that pretence. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> commandeth <hi>thee to obey for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake;</hi> but you pretend Conſcience for Diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience and Rebellion: He commands <hi>you to be ſubject for Conſcience ſake,</hi> you pretend to be free for Conſcience ſake: theſe are Contradictions, and are repugnant one to another. Theſe are not doubful Caſes, the Rule is too plain here to admit of Scruples. That the way to Peace may be plain, you muſt not through Ignorance, Prejudice or Precipitancy, call thoſe things Popery and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition which are not, nor perſwade your Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers with ſo much Imbitterneſs againſt them: be not ſo loud againſt them, decry them not only with Noyſe and Bawling, bring them to the Teſt and let all things be weigh'd by the Balances of the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary; and then it will be eaſily ſeen what is really Popery and Superſtition, and what ſo pretended. Religion is for the moſt part taken up upon Truſt, Cuſtom and Education rather than Choice; frame it for us, and we follow therein our Parents and our Nurſes. They call every thing Popery that is not made uſe of by themſelves: Every one that pleads for Ceremonies, though never ſo decent, is eſteemed Popiſhly affected; and generally among the common People of your Perſwaſion, Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy is thought no better of than Popery, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates and Miniſters of the Church of <hi>England</hi> than of Cardinals and Prieſts. But my Maſters 'tis a hard Caſe, that thoſe very Perſons who were the chief Inſtruments of breaking the Tyrannical Yoke of <hi>Rome</hi> in this Nation, and for which many of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66156:10"/>them were Martyred, ſhould be they who fram'd thoſe very Conſtitutions which you call Popiſh, and for which they loſt their Lives by Popiſh Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries. And alſo that they ſhould be eſteemed Popiſh Abettors, becauſe of their approving of theſe Ceremonies who have ſo ſtrenuouſly wrot againſt the Tenets of <hi>Rome,</hi> and who like worthy Champions have ſtood in the Gap and defended the true Proteſtant Cauſe againſt all gainſayers. That theſe very Perſons who have Converted many from the Popiſh Religion, have Eſtabliſh'd many that were Wavering, have Recover'd others that were Lapſed, and that have Confirmed ſeveral that were Doubting; that theſe (I ſay) ſhould be Branded by you with the Ignominious mark of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, is ſtrange and hardly Parallel'd. And laſtly, that this deſired Unity may be brought about, you are deſired to uſe ſo much Charity as not raſhly to damn another for every Difference, and ſo much Ingenuity as not to render the Opinions of your Adverſaries more black and odious to the World than you in your Conſciences know them to be. Since the Church of <hi>England</hi> has Juſtified her ſelf by ſome of the unanſwerable Writings of her wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Sons, from all Imputations of Hereſie and Schiſm, from all novelty and falſe Doctrine, and Anſwered all Objections whatſoever againſt her Ceremonies and Diſcipline.</p>
            <p>There is yet one other Stone of offence, which I had almoſt forgot, and which will help to Unity if it be may be roll'd away, for many other leſſer gravelly adherences will be avoided
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66156:11"/>with it, and this is an Opinion, <hi>That it is unlawful, and ſinful, to do any thing without direction from the Scripture or the Word of God,</hi> whereby you think by that means to overthrow the Cerimonies of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> But, I will ſay, in the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Dr. <hi>Sanderſons</hi> own words,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sand. ad cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Ser.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 62.</note> 
               <hi>That if you will under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this only of the Subſtantials of Gods Worſhip, and of the exerciſes of Spiritual and Supernatural Graces, the aſſertion is true and ſound; but if you extend it as you do to all the actions of common Life whatſoever, whether Natural or Civil, it is altogether falſe and indefenſible.</hi> I ſhall not go about to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute this Opinion, 'tis not my Buſineſs or Intention to enter into Diſputes of the Merits of the Cauſe, it has been ſufficiently done by more skilful Hands and learned Pens: But this Weapon is ſo made that it may be turned againſt your own ſelves, it offends as much as defends you, and cuts both ways like a two edged Sword; for by that Rule you can no more defend the wearing your ſhort Cloaks and little Bands, than the other party their Gowns and Rochetts; and it will be as difficult to prove from Scripture your Inſtitutions and Formalities, as the other their Ceremonies and Cuſtoms. The Holy Word of God is a perfect and moſt abſolute and ſufficient direction as to all things concerning our Salvation, and as to that point we need not the help of Traditions; but certainly in things indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, and in things about the common Actions of Life, we need not ſeek any farther than the Light of Reaſon and the common Rules of Diſcretion, and not expect particular Warrants only from the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66156:11"/>Scripture for every action of humane Life. All that we are to take care of is that our Actions be regulated as near as may be to thoſe Rules laid down in the Holy Scriptures for us to walk by, at leaſt that they be no ways contradictory; and then it will be ſufficient to maintain their Legality, whilſt they are eſtabliſhed by the Law of Nature or that of Reaſon, without ſeeking to deduce Authority for them out of the Holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the chief things that at preſent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur to my Memory which lye in the way that leads to Peace and Unity, and which if removed will render the way more plain and eaven. Theſe are not things of Indifferency, you will not own them nor plead for them, and I queſtion not, when you have lay'd aſide your imbittered Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and rigid Diſpoſitions againſt your Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, you will be willing to put to your Hands, that all theſe Stones of offence may be done away, and which ſhould not have been mentioned but for that end. But I would not have you think that I am Partial, and that this Call ought not alſo to be heard on the other ſide, and that I would not incite thoſe alſo of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to do their part in every thing that may be juſtly required of them. And here I cannot but juſtifie them from any aſperſion of that Nature, in that in all their Writings they have held out to you the right Hand of fellowſhip, they have invited you to come in to them, they have Called to Unity, they have deſired your Fellowſhip, and that there may be no longer this Diſtance and Separation, they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66156:12"/>have at all times exhibited a willingneſs to have this breach made up; they would receive you into their Churches, they would Communicate with you as Brothers, they would provide for you as Sons, they would take care of you as Fathers, if you would own them as ſuch. What then makes this breach? What is it continues this Separation? What makes you ſo ſtiff in things of ſmall moment? Why ſhould not they yeild? Say you; why ſhould not you obey? Say they. One would think the weight of Authority ſhould in this Caſe caſt the ballance: but ſure you have put ſomething more into the ſcales than what appears to the World, that neither the kindneſs ſhown you by your Oppoſers, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence of Princes nor the commands of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity are able to move up your heavy ſcale. But I would alſo have this Call reach to the Ears of thoſe of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to whom with Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Submiſſion be it ſpoken, that you are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo deſired to continue to uſe all means that this Unity may be effected, and that you would on your parts endeavour to remove all Obſtacles thereto: You muſt then endeavour to forget all that is paſt, you muſt not remember our late Troubles, Wars, Confuſions, Devaſtations, as the effects of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy War for Religion; you muſt not tell them any more of their unſanctified and bloody Covenant, you muſt not ſay they are a ſtiff-necked Generation and people of a perverſe Mind and Heart; you muſt not mention their proud and arrogant Tryers, nor fright them with the Hobgoblin <hi>Smectymnnus;</hi> you muſt now forget all that's paſt and continue that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66156:12"/>kindneſs and moderation that moſt of you have ſtill on all occaſions ſhown them, that the diſtance that is yet between you may be overcome, and that you may meet as Brothers, and be united in Heart and Spirit.</p>
            <p>Theſe Rubs being preſuppoſed to be removed, what is it now that you Contend for? Things as you your ſelves ſay of ſmall moment, trifles, Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, &amp;c. 'Tis true they are not Eſſentials, matters of Faith, things of abſolute neceſſity to Salvation, things of indifferency; yet not trifles and of no weight or value. If they be as you ſay, why ſtand you ſo ſtiff againſt them? Why all this buſtle and do about nothing? But you have a refuge, Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. They plead the ſame for retaining them, and alſo have Antiquity and Authority to back them. Common Prayer will not down with you, no ſet Form, it ſtints the Spirit, with other ſmall and fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous objections againſt ſome parts of the Liturgie. For ſhame leave off at laſt thoſe needleſs Cavils of which ſome of your ſelves have been aſhamed. You know that Forms of Prayer have been in all Ages both in the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Churches, and are not only of a primitive Inſtitution in the very Infancy of the Church, when there was a double meaſure of the Spirit poured down upon its Biſhops and Paſtors, but our Lord <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> himſelf thought good to leave a Set and preſcribed Form of Prayer, and alſo the like Forms were uſed of old in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church and Service, they were not left to their own Inventions. I will not go about to argue the Caſe with you, but if it be Lawful to Pray in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66156:13"/>a ſet Form, as I ſuppoſe none of you will gainſay, it is then expedient becauſe Commanded by Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. But have you not a Chriſtian Liberty left you to exerciſe your Gifts and to ſhew your Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and Parts in Prayer <hi>Ex tempore</hi> before your Sermons? And that the Spirit may not be quench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as you ſay, may you not enlarge your ſelves? And is it not an uſual practice in our Churches? Why then ſhould you ſcruple ſo much at our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie? Would you have none? But all the Gifted and Ungifted left to their own Inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions? In your time had you not a Directory? What was it but a Form of Worſhip after your Mode? And what Church is there abroad, even <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva</hi> it ſelf, without ſome Forms both of Worſhip and of Prayer. That our Book of Common Prayer was taken out of the Maſs Book, and that it was the Maſs in <hi>Engliſh</hi> as many of the ignorant have been Taught, to caſt the greater Odium upon it, is an Impoſture enough diſcover'd and unmask'd. Speak out, is there any thing Sinful or Unlawful in the Liturgie? Or that is not agreeable to Gods Word? Prove but that and then you do ſomething, for the Church holds in her Articles of Religion, <hi>That it is not Lawful for her to ordain any thing that is contrary or beſides the Word of God.</hi> Beſides have not your requeſts been gratified in many things, in altering ſeveral paſſages in the Liturgie, as in the Offices of Marriage, Churching of Women and Burials; what is it you would then have all or none? Cannot you be pleaſed without it be whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caſt aſide? Will no Conceſſions elſe ſerve your
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66156:13"/>turn? O that you would make ſome weighty ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions and not uſe ſuch a frivolous and vain Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>villing againſt it not worth the Anſwering, or that you would ſhew the World one of your own that were better before you take away this; that would be reaſonable and worthy your undertaking. And ſince ſome of you have allowed of a Liturgie, and for peace ſake of many inconvenient Circumſtances in Gods Worſhip,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Baxt. Diſp. p.</hi> 487. <hi>Safe way. p.</hi> 198.</note> and acknowledg alſo that the Governors of the Church have a deciſive power in things undetermined in Scripture; why ſhould you not yield to accept of this equitable Propoſition, to accept of and Conform to this Form of Prayer and theſe Rites of the Church, till better be Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted or Ordained.</p>
            <p>As to the Croſs in Baptiſm a Moral <hi>Hiroglyphick</hi> only of our Saviours Death and Crucifixion, God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers and Godmothers, Confirmation, Kneeling at the Sacrament, Bowing at the Name of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up at Reading the Creed, and other things of the like Nature; are theſe things worthy to cauſe an Eternal Separation betwixt you? Are they of ſo great moment as to make ſo wide and long a breach in a Nation? Are they of worth and value to make you run into Contempt and Rebellion? Let us know your Minds, if any of theſe ſhould be yeild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to your tender Conſciences and diſuſed, to pleaſe you, would you then Conform in all the reſt? Would not your Anſwer be as formerly to Queen <hi>Elizabeth?</hi> That you would not leave a Hoof be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind. All the Ceremonies of the Church muſt be laid aſide, you would have a naked Religion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66156:14"/>Cloaths, which is not ſeemly. Ceremonies are but the Garments and decencies of Religion, not part of it but ſomewhat that it cannot well be ſeen without, they are like our Cloaths that may be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, that may be cut to the mode and ſize of the Times without altering the form of our Body. There have been Laws made for prohibiting the uſe of ſome Garments and that have injoyned the wearing of others, though before it was at the choice of the People to wear or not wear them, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch Laws made they were no longer indiffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. It is even ſo of our Ceremonies, they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different things of themſelves, but being injoyned by Authority they are now no longer ſo; Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is no indifferent thing, that is abſolutely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned by the Word of God; 'tis obedience to Eccleſiaſtical Laws that is required. This obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is either juſtly due to theſe Laws or it is not: If it is, why then do you diſobey? If you ſay it is not,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13.</note> you contradict the Scriptures, <hi>Submit to every Ordinance of Man, whether it be unto the King as Supream or unto Governors &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</note> 
               <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the higher Powers.</hi> However it is the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt way to obey, ſhould they Command things doubtful, let the blame lie upon them, you will be excuſed. God requires not impoſſibilities: But cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly God has given to the Governors of the Church a Power of making Laws and Canons: <hi>Let all things be done decently and according to order.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40</note> And according to this Rule of the Apoſtle, the Rites and Ceremonies of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are as few, decent, comly and fitting, as in any
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:66156:14"/>Church of the Chriſtian World; and all Exceptions againſt them that I ever could yet ſee, empty and of no ſubſtance.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Manton</hi> on <hi>Jude.</hi>
               </note> Some of you have told us there are but two Lawful Cauſes of Separation from the Church, Perſecution and a general corruption of Doctrine: for both theſe Cauſes and no other have we Separated from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and if you can prove theſe two marks of Separation to be inherent to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> you will have ſufficient to ground your Separation as Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and have ſome plea for what you do; but till then, I beſeech you, ſet your face towards the Temple of Obedience and be refractory no longer; and ſince theſe things which make this Breach be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween you are not of any great Moment, are but Ceremonies and the outward Garments and Garna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of Religion; leave off that obſtinacy and <hi>ſubmit your ſelves to the Ordinance of Man for the Lords ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The great Cry that you have made againſt theſe Rites and Ceremonies of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church hath been, that they were <hi>Popery</hi> and of Popiſh extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, borrowed from the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> but all this while you tell us not what <hi>Popery</hi> is, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can you diſown or diſſent from all that is held or practiſed by the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> Certainly our Forefathers to whom we owe theſe things, our Reformation from the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church and the Purity of our Religion, would not have laid down their Lives and have been Martyr'd by the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> if it had then been thought either by themſelves or by the others that what they had
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66156:15"/>done as to the Reforming the Ceremonies of the Church, or towards the maintaining the Doctrines they Held, or that the Orders and Diſcipline they had Conſtituted had been Popery or rather not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite in ſome meaſure thereto. As by Diſſenting ſhe ſhewed the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> that ſhe had no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency upon her, and that ſhe ſo far diſowned her as ſhe had diſowned God, by laying aſide all thoſe groſs Corruptions for which our Church Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from her; ſo on the other ſide, by retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome of her harmleſs and innocent Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, they ſhew'd her they did not do any thing by the Spirit of Oppoſition only, whereby they might take offence without having a juſt ground and cauſe for it. But Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to his Sermons tells you what in Truth Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sand. Pref. Sect.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>That it is thoſe Doctrines which are contrary to the Word of God or but ſuperadded thereunto as neceſſary Points of Faith to be of all Chriſtians Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved under pain of Damnation; and all thoſe Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitions uſed in the Worſhip of God which either are <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful as being contrary to the Word of God, or being not contrary and therefore Arbitrary or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different are made Eſſentials and impoſed as neceſſary parts of Worſhip.</hi> From all which the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath been ſufficiently Vindicated and Cleared, and you cannot but know in your own Conſciences that ſhe diſowns the ſhaddow of all thoſe things, and you abuſe her when you tax her of Popery or Superſtition by reaſon of her Rites and Ceremonies. But you too often con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Superſtition and Idolatry together, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66156:15"/>the keeping of Chriſtmas is Superſtitious, the Croſs, the Surplice, the Common Prayer Book, the Holy Days, the Vigils, Lent, all Superſtitious: and ſometimes 'tis the Idol Chriſtmas, the Idol Common Prayer Book, the Idol Saints Days, and the like. But as you know what Idolatry is, the giving an Holy and Religious Worſhip to any thing that is only due to our Maker the only true God; ſo you may know alſo, that Superſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not the doing or omitting of any thing more or leſs than is neceſſary in matters of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by reaſon of the Obligation laid upon them by Superiors; but it is the performing or not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming thoſe things by reaſon of a neceſſity that is laid upon them that they are ſinful of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, whereby the Conſciences of Men are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaved and terrified. And by this means all things that you Judge to be Unlawful though indifferent in themſelves, till commanded by Authority, you prohibit under the Obligation of Sin, thereby im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing on the Conſciences of others a neceſſity of not uſing them, though commanded by Authority, as being of themſelves vile and ſinful; and this is truly Superſtition.</p>
            <p>But what is it you would have? Would you have no Government? No Diſcipline? No Form in the Church? If any, why not this as is already Eſtabliſhed? Since you are not able to Convince it or Convict it either of Popery or Superſtition? You would have your own, you think that purer and better, but you muſt then ſtay till you can Convince the Magiſtrate alſo, you muſt Convince
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:66156:16"/>your King and Governors, make them firſt of your Perſwaſion, exhibit to them your Arguments, your Reaſons, your Perſwaſions, all you have done hitherto is nothing; you ſee Thouſands are not of your Mind and they will not believe your Church Government and your Claſſical Form to be any ways Quadrate with ſuch a Monarchy as this is; it may perhaps be fit for a ſmall City, a little Commonwealth, a Province or ſo, it may be fitted for the Conſtitution of <hi>Geneva</hi> or ſome <hi>Cantons</hi> of the <hi>Switzers,</hi> but it can never be made to ſit well about the Necks of theſe three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms; neither will you be able to perſwade the King to pull down the Biſhops to ſet up arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and boundleſs Tryers, to lay aſide the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Liturgie</hi> and to bring in its place your <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory,</hi> to put down Eccleſiaſtical Courts and ſet up Commiſſioners; we have had too late tryal of your Way, and the Tyranny of your Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment cannot ſo ſoon be forgotten, when eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Heads of your Claſſes were as Abſolute as Popes, and your Inferior Clergy as Proud as Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals. But had the King and State a mind to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie you and to ſet up your Form, would not there ſtill be as many Diſſenters, for you are not yet agreed among your ſelves, you have not yet ſhaped a Form that would pleaſe others, the <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent, Anabaptiſt, Quaker,</hi> Cry out againſt it and had rather live under the Rule of the Biſhops than under the rigid Government of Presbytery; it will be impoſſible to pleaſe you all, and you may as ſoon hope to fit a Garment for the Moon.
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:66156:16"/>Till you are agreed then of a better Form of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Government, and that you are able to Convince the King and the State and your other Diſſenting Brethren, that you have a better and one more agreeable to the Conſtitution of this Nation, to the Primitive Inſtitution and Purity, without the unlawful Argument of the Sword and Rebellion; ſubmit, I ſay, in Gods Name and for Conſcience ſake to this as is ſet up, and be no longer Separatiſts, and Congregate no longer by your ſelves, but be perſwaded, as you ought, to hearken to the Call both of God and Man, of the Scriptures that preſs you to Unity and Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, of your Brethren that invite you to Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity and Communion, and to your Superiors, who Command you to Submiſſion and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>As to the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> you have not wherewith to find any the leaſt ſhaddow of Cavilling againſt it, you cannot but Confeſs its Principles to be found; but all your Pique is againſt its Diſcipline or Church Regiment, which, as the Learned and Rational Mr.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hooker Law of Eccl. Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Sect.</hi> 3</note> 
               <hi>Hooker</hi> tells you, is a thing different from Matters of Faith and Salvation. But who is it that ought to lay down the Rules and matters of Church Polity, and to frame the Laws and Conſtitutions of Church Government? Are they not Men? And ſuch to whoſe care the Governance of the Church is Committed? To Kings the Nurſing Fathers, and to ſubordinate Miniſters, as Biſhops, &amp;c? Would you have all Laws already laid down
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:66156:17"/>in Scripture? And nothing left for the exerciſe of the Light of Reaſon in theſe matters? But there is no doubt but theſe Laws of Eccleſiaſtical Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty may be made by Man Legally, and by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luminis na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turalis dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere, non mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ſtultum eſt ſed &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. Lib. 4 de Trin. Cap. 6.</note> and in which Man may make uſe of his Reaſon, following therein the Rules of the Law of God and the Law of Nature, which in the ſubſtance is one with the Moral Law of the Scripture; and alſo though theſe Humane or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non Laws be not expreſly ſet down in any part of the Scripture, yet they ought upon unerring Principles to be deduced therefrom, or at leaſt without Contradiction unto any poſitive Law or Command in Scripture. By this means the Laws of Man may be ſaid to be the Laws of God: For he owns the very Laws of the Heathen to be of himſelf, though framed by the Light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture only, and by him written in their Hearts, by which the Gentiles were either Excuſed or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned.
<note place="margin">2 <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.</note> Why then fly you from theſe Laws as ſuch Bug-bears? Why do you not in all Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Singleneſs of Heart yield Obedience to them for the Lords ſake? Where lies the Illega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of them. Becauſe you cannot find Lawn Sleeves and Rochets in Scripture, therefore muſt they not be worn? And becauſe you do not Read of Gowns, Tippets, ſquare Caps and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical Girdles, therefore 'tis unlawful for Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to wear them? When God gave us the Light of the Scripture he did not take from us the Light of Reaſon, this indeed is but a dim Light in reſpect of the other, and ought not be truſted
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:66156:17"/>to in matters of Faith, Divine and Supernatural things; but being in Conjunction with the greater Light of Gods Word, we have a clear and perfect Sun-ſhine to ſee as far as an Humane condition will permit of into the buſineſs both of Doctrine and Mannors, and we are thereby inabled to give Rules in matters of Faith and Life. For though the Scripture is a perfect and abſolute Rule in it ſelf and contains all things within it ſelf as to what belongs to our Salvation, yet it is no ways derogatory from its fullneſs and ſufficiency to ſay that we cannot make uſe of this Rule without the Light of our Reaſon: and alſo that in Civil things we may with a Chriſtian Liberty do many things that we find not in Scripture, by the meer uſe of Reaſon alone, and that very Lawfully and without Sin, ſo thoſe things be not contradicto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Word of God. If then our Governors have a Power given them that they may Ordain and Conſtitute divers Ceremonies in the Church, though not mentioned and found in Scripture, then ought Inferiors to ſubmit to ſuch Laws and Rules, and are in Duty bound to obſerve them, when they are injoyned by a Lawful Authority. Do but conſider with your ſelves that whilſt you ſo ſtrictly Demand Scripture to be ſhown for the uſe of Ceremonies and other things made uſe of in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> may not others with the like Liberty bid you to ſhow what Example or Command you have in Scripture for your Lay Presbyters, your Claſſes, your ſtone Churches, your Tythes, your Infant Sprinklings, your Singing Pſalms, your
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:66156:18"/>Weekly Sabbath; all theſe things you know have been Objected againſt you, to which you led the Way and opened the Gap by ſuch your unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Demands.</p>
            <p>If Man hath not a Liberty given him to make uſe of his Reaſon in Ordering the Affairs of the Church, or in altering many things and adding others as may be Convenient to the temper and conſtitution of Times but muſt have a Precedent or Command for it expreſly in Scripture; how did <hi>David</hi> err when he thought to build a Temple at <hi>Jeruſalem?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.2, 3 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.5. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 7.6 7.30.23.</note> Which the Prophet approved of: Or <hi>Solomon</hi> for keeping a Feaſt of ſeven days for the Dedication of the Altar? Or <hi>Hezekiah</hi> for continuing the Feaſt of Unleavened Bread ſeven days longer than the time appointed by the Law? Or <hi>Mordecai</hi> for making an Ordinance for the Yearly obſervation of the Feaſt of <hi>Purim?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſth.</hi> 9.27.</note> The building of Synagogues, wearing of Sackcloth and Aſhes in ſign of Humiliation: their Faſts, more then were Commanded immediately by God,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zach.</hi> 8.19.</note> were all of Humane Inſtitution and without doubt Lawful. Times alter, and what at one Time may be thought Fitting and Harmleſs, at another would be accounted Scandalous and Unfitting, as that <hi>Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum Charitatis</hi> uſed in the Times of the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and approved of by them,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.12</note> would now give Cauſe of offence, and thoſe <hi>Agapae</hi> or Love Feaſts uſed by the Primitive Chriſtians, at firſt Innocent enough, but ſoon grew to be worthy of Reproof by the Apoſtle.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> There is Milk for Babes and Meat for ſtronger Men. There is a difference between the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:66156:18"/>Church in its Infancy and after the growth of ſo many Years. It has been Corrupted and grown four on its Lees, and it hath been again Purged and Refined, therefore there muſt of neceſſity have been ſeveral Laws, Rules, Canons and Inſtitutions framed for its ſeveral Diſpenſations, moſt agreeable to the temper of the Ages and the Times in which they were made: And the Orders of the Times of the Apoſtles themſelves are not in all things now to be urged as of abſolute neceſſity.</p>
            <p>I cannot but wonder ſince that theſe Ceremonies and Rites of the Church are by you accounted of but as Mint and Cummin, nay by ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as Toys, Trifles and Follies, that you ſhould ſtand ſo ſtifly againſt them; but thoſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> thinking not ſo meanly of them, have therefore the more Reaſon to ſtand for their Continuance. They ſay there ought to be a bowing of the Knee as well as of the Heart. That by outward Actions the Mind is ſtirred up with greater fervency to Attention and Devotion. That Solemnities have been in all Ages, both in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Divine matters as well as Civil: That theſe things are neceſſary and of uſe as Garments to the Body: That without them Religion would appear Naked and Uncomly: That they are alſo Edifying and Significant: That they move the Heart and the Affections, and that they are of great uſe and force: That they have been Inſtituted not without great Care and Deliberation by Holy, Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Learned Men: That they have been long Confirmed in the Minds of Men: That to alter or
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:66156:19"/>aboliſh them would be Dangerous and Scandalous: That they are Harmleſs and Innocent of themſelves: That they give not the Offence, but that it is taken Unjuſtly againſt them: That under the Uſe of them the Land hath long flouriſhed with Peace and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity till our late diſtracted Times: That ſince God hath again Reſtored them almoſt Miraculouſly when they were thought to be Dead and for ever Extinguiſhed. Theſe things Conſidered, and that they appear not ſuch Trifles to them as you account them, they have more Reaſon not to Depart from them, and you leſs to Inſiſt upon their Aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>But alas 'tis not only Ceremony that you would take way, but the Root and Branch (as you are wont to ſay) of Epiſcopacy; the Biſhops it ſeems are alſo Popery: they muſt not ſtand, but is not Self all the while at the Bottom? Is it not that you may Reign in their ſtead with your Lay Elders? And what is this <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> ſo much Cry'd out againſt by you and others of your Diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtamp? I'll tell you in the Learned Mr. <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingworth</hi>'s Words, <hi>Epiſcopacy in the Eſſentiality of it is an appointment of one Man of eminent Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Sufficiency to have a Care of all the Churches within a certain Precinct or Dioceſs, furniſhed with Authority (not Abſolute or Arbitrary but Regulated by Laws) to the intent that all the Churches under him may be provided of Good and Able Pastors or Presbyters.</hi> This is the Government you are ſo ſcandaliz'd at and which you would take away, being the Inſtitution of <hi>Christ</hi> himſelf who made
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:66156:19"/>his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> Biſhops or Overſeers of his Church, for <hi>Matthias</hi> was choſen to an Epiſcopal Office <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. And St.
<note place="margin">Act. 1. Cyp. l. 3. Ep. 9</note> 
               <hi>Cyprian</hi> calls all the <hi>Apostles</hi> by the ſame Name <hi>Epiſcopos.</hi> And although they had a large Commiſſion from Chriſt, <hi>Go Baptize all Nations,</hi> and ſeem Indefinite, yet we find ſome of them Biſhops by Reſtraint, as St. <hi>James</hi> at <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> took to himſelf the Care of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and St. <hi>Peter</hi> of the <hi>Jews,</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> took Charge of <hi>Aſia</hi> the Leſs, where were afterwards ſeven Churches governed by ſo many Biſhops term<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by St. <hi>John</hi> Angels.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.</note> And the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves appointed others as <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi> at firſt Agents only in their ſtead, and afterwards with <hi>Apostolical</hi> power of their own. And if there be any Credit to be given to Hiſtory and to Antiquity it ſelf, we find that <hi>Linus</hi> was made Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> by the Apoſtles,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iren. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3</note> 
               <hi>Polycarpus</hi> of <hi>Smyrna, Evodius</hi> of <hi>Antioch</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> of <hi>Creet;</hi> Erecting Churches in all theſe places where the Goſpel of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> was Received, all having the ſame Faith, the ſame Sacraments, and the ſame Form of Government; ſo as they ſeemed but one Body and in a perfect Unity one with another, that every thing might be done with Decency and in Order. <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Euſchius</hi> have given us whole Catalogues of Biſhops ſucceſſively to their Times, and we find them nominated in many <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories</hi> and Writings of Old, and from their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning deduced down to our Times. This is the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment you would have pull'd down, this is one Form you oppoſe, a Government of Divine Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:66156:20"/>by that of the Holy Ghoſt conferred on the Apoſtles, and by them on others, and ſo ſucceſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Church in all Ages and thorow all times by Ordination and Laying on of Hands, ſo that there can hardly be manifeſted a more plain and evident Truth.</p>
            <p>I am not Ignorant that you admit of the Name of <hi>Biſhops</hi> and of <hi>Presbyters,</hi> but would make them of equal Authority; you would indeed be all Biſhops or Popes rather, Subjection and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence are things that have ſeem'd very ſcandalous to you. But there is nothing more plain than that Biſhops had not only the preheminency of Order but of Rule alſo. And as there were in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, the High Prieſt, the Inferior Prieſt, and the <hi>Levites,</hi> who were not only differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in Order and Superiority, but there was a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction, ſo that the one might do what the other might not do, the <hi>Levites</hi> might not Intrench on the Office of the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and the <hi>Prieſts</hi> could not enter into the <hi>Sanctum Sanctorum.</hi> So in the Church of Chriſt the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> the <hi>Presbyters</hi> and the <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons</hi> were diſtinct in Order and Office; the <hi>Deacons</hi> were ſubſervient to the <hi>Presbyters,</hi> and they to the <hi>Biſhop</hi> to whom the Power of Rule and Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was only given; and the Preſbyters again re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived theirs of Adminiſtring the Sacraments, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpenſing the Word, &amp;c. from them, being by them Ordained thereto. The Biſhops are the Fathers, the other the Children; they Command not as Lords and Arbitrarily, theſe obey not as Slaves but as Sons; they Rule, and theſe obey according
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:66156:20"/>to the Word of God and according to that Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Inſtitution which made that excellent Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, all things being done for the Glory of God. I know the many long and tedious Cavils and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputes which ſome of the moſt Subtle of you have entred into about this thing, and what duſt you have raiſed about this Juriſdiction: But it has been all laid, and none that have Eyes but can ſee clearly into the matter, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> gave Power to his Apoſtles to Rule and Govern his Church, and that the ſame Power was by them Conferred to others,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.15. <hi>Matt.</hi> 10.24. <hi>Matt.</hi> 28.19 20.</note> and ſo ſhall continue to the end of the World according to Chriſts Commiſſion. But if you cannot find in Scripture that you ought to ſubmit to Biſhops as your Fathers, I hope you will believe Mr. <hi>Calvin,</hi> and for his ſake have at leaſt a better Opinion of them, who ſays,
<note place="margin">Calvin. Epiſt. ad Card. Sandolet.</note> 
               <hi>Nullo non ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themate dignos Arbitror, qui ſe Epiſcopis libentiſſime non ſubmittunt. I think them worthy of a Curſe, who do not willingly ſubmit themſelves to Biſhops.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Open then your Eyes at laſt and look not ſo aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quint on this Form of Government, and more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly as it is here Eſtabliſh'd in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which certainly is the moſt like and comes neareſt to the Primitive Inſtitution of the Apoſtles, and the next Ages, of any Church in the World, both for the Purity of its Doctrine and the Order of its Government; its Ceremonies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both Few and Decent, and its Power regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Juſt Laws. And as one ſays,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vindication of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Clergy. p.</hi> 50.</note> 
               <hi>The Church of</hi> England <hi>is a body of ſo firm a Constitution, and ſo excellently Temper'd, and ſo well Shap'd, and of ſo
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:66156:21"/>clear a Strength and Vigor in all its Limbs, that no outward Force is able to Injure it: nothing but ſome inward Corruption and decay in the Vital parts that can poſſibly bring it to the Ground.</hi> Indeed you had trip'd up its Heels and lay'd it along, but it was but a Foil, you ſee how ſoon it aroſe again; and in that little Interſpace or <hi>Interregnum,</hi> as I may term it, what horrid Confuſions were amongſt us? With all your Arts you could not hinder others from inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding your Province. Inſtead of Surplices you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held Scarlet Cloaks, Wigs and Swords, as Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to thoſe who Preached in your Pulpits; nay the very Women invading the Chair and challeng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Liberty, though expreſly contrary to the Rule of the Apoſtle. You ſaw what ill Steers<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men you were and how the Ship of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth thrived under your Government, in what danger of Drowning or of being Split upon the Rocks or Periſhing in the Quickſands. Methinks this little Tryal might Convince you of the Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Imbecillity of the one, and the Firmneſs and excellent Temper of the other Government; by which this Land has ſo long Flouriſhed, and which is ſo fitted not only to Monarchy, making that Maxim good, as we by Experience ſaw, <hi>no Biſhop, no King,</hi> but alſo to the Temper and Conſtitution of the People of <hi>England;</hi> that there can be no better Government ever thought on, which ſhall be here ſo well Approved and Received. It is not only my Opinion but of many more the moſt Eminent and Learned of the Nation, and thoſe not of ſmall Repute and who have been Able to give ſufficient
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:66156:21"/>Proof to maintain their good Opinion of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of our preſent Form of Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and among the reſt the Learned Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> has theſe Words,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pref. Sect.</hi> 1.</note> which he ſets down as his full Perſwaſion, <hi>Surely the preſent Form of Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which the Laws of this Land have Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed, is ſuch as no Law of God nor Reaſon of Man hath hitherto been alledged of force ſufficient to prove they do ill, who to the uttermoſt of their power with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the alteration thereof. And contrarywiſe, The other which inſtead of it we are required to accept is only by Error and Miſconceit named the Ordinanee of</hi> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>no one proof as yet brought forth whereby it may clearly appear to be ſo in very deed.</hi> And theſe two Aſſertions he hath ſo fully and unanſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably Maintained in his excellent Book of the Laws of <hi>Eccleſiastical Polity,</hi> that methinks you ſhould lay your Finger on your Mouths and no longer ſpeak againſt this Form of Church Government, nor remain at this Diſtance and in this ſtate of Separation, till you have found out better Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for to Juſtifie your ſo doing, than thoſe you have yet made known to the World.</p>
            <p>However low and mean Opinion you have of this Form of Church Government as it is now Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd in <hi>England,</hi> 'tis otherwiſe reſpected abroad: By others 'tis look'd upon with Envy and Admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: The beauty of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is not ſo Deſpicable as her Diſſenting Sons would make it: She ſhines and glitters in the Eyes of her Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors: She appears White and Innocent to thoſe who behold her: She is Brightned by the Flames
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:66156:22"/>of her Martyrs, and comes forth of thoſe perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Fires with Purity and Glory: She is look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as a Matron gravely Adorned with her Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, they are Rich and all of Value, not Gaudy, Cumberſom or Fantaſtick: She is <hi>Stupor Mundi</hi> the amazement (as one ſays) of the World for Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Piety and Religion: Her Doctrines are Sound, her Principles Firm, her Integrity Noted: She is full of Love and Meekneſs: She is a perfect hater of Perſecution: She had rather Suffer than do an injury: in Fine ſhe is the Light, Glory and Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of the whole Chriſtian World; yet ſhe is not proud, ſhe Lords it not over Mens Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; ſhe ſtoops to win with Love; ſhe ſtretches out her Arms to embrace thoſe who fly from her; ſhe Invites and Wooes thoſe that ſhun her; ſhe does all ſhe can that there may be an Unity and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity through the whole Land; and certainly we may Cry out with the Poet,
<q>
                  <hi>O Fortunatos nimium ſua ſi bona norint Angligenos</hi> —</q> But what in the mean time do her Unnatural and Diſobedient Sons? They beſpatter her Reputation, they fling dirt in her Face, they endeavor to pollute her Garments, they would render her Odious, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtical, Ridiculous; they Call her Whore and compare her with <hi>Babylon;</hi> they treat her after an evil ſort and give By-names to all her Ornaments. But though <hi>ſhe is deſpiſed and rejected of Men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53.3. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.50 51</note> 
               <hi>one full of ſorrows and acquainted with griefs;</hi> yet ſhe Crys out with <hi>David, This is my Comfort in my Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction:
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:66156:22"/>for thy Word hath Quickned me. The Proud have had me greatly in Deriſion: yet I have not De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined from thy Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lay aſide now your Paſſions I beſeech you, <hi>Put off your former Converſation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.22, 23 25</note> 
               <hi>and be Renewed in the Spirit of your Mind: Speak every Man truth with his Neighbour, for we are Members one of another: Chriſt is our Head. There is but one Body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">15 4, 5, 6</note> 
               <hi>one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, one Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm, one God and Father of all.</hi> O do but conſider the Beauty of Unity, let it Allure you, let it break your Stifneſs, let it move you to run into the open Arms of your Mother, and to be knit in the Bands of Amity with your Brethren.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 133.</note> Conſider <hi>how Good and how Pleaſant it is for Brethren to dwell together in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: It is like precious ointment upon the Head: like the Dew of</hi> Hermon <hi>Hill; and like that which falls upon the Mountains of</hi> Sion.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>It will make you like a Tree planted by the Rivers of Waters.</hi> Ye will be no longer Barren but Fruitful: How Happy and Bleſſed then would the Nation be! The Nations round about us would Tremble, and our Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries would be Confounded. O that there were a full Aſſent and Conſent among you both in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituals as well as Temporals! It is not enough that you Live together, that you Trade together, that you Converſe one with another; but to Compleat your Happineſs, you muſt Pray together, and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip together, that Compleats the Friendſhip. The Heathen Orator can tell you,
<note place="margin">Tul. de Amic.</note> 
               <hi>Amicitia eſt Divina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Humanarum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> rerum ſumma cum benevolentia Conſenſio.</hi> 'Tis that makes the true Harmony, that
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:66156:23"/>is the trueſt Friendſhip: an Agreement with the higheſt good Will, or as I may ſay, with one Heart and Mind in Divine things as well as in Humane things, in Church as well as in State, in Worſhip as well as in Traffick, in Spiritual Communion as well as Worldly Commerce, in Traffick for Heavenly Treaſure as much as for Periſhable Goods. I ſay, let the Shine and Luſtre of this Glorious State move you to ſet ſome ſteps towards this Unity. Ye have been too long aſunder, why ſhould there be any Difference between <hi>Benjamin</hi> and <hi>Judah?</hi> Meet, I ſay, at laſt as Brethren; come with willing Hearts and Minds. The <hi>Goliah</hi> of Oppoſition may be eaſily Slain; one ſingle Stone will ſink that <hi>Philiſtin.</hi> Let ſome among you ſet an Example, others will follow. Conſider the Peace of <hi>Iſrael</hi> more than your own Intereſt, and think how you will Strengthen the Hands of your Brethren by this ſo much deſired Unity and happy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity.</p>
            <p>Hearken, I beſeech you, to the Crys and Calls of your Brethren, they cannot be Wounded but you muſt Suffer: Now is the time before it be too late. <hi>Sow to your ſelves in Righteouſneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10.12.8.</note> 
               <hi>and you ſhall Reap in Mercy.</hi> The time will come elſe, that <hi>you will Call to the Mountains to cover you, and the Hills to fall on you.</hi> You will be driven into your holes like Conies. Have a care that you become not like <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14.23.</note> 
               <hi>an habitation for the Bittern, and for ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Pools of Water; and that God does not at laſt ſweep you with the beſom of Deſtruction.</hi> There is now a greater neceſſity than ever, that you ſhould
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:66156:23"/>be no longer divided; you are weakned like a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver cut into many Streams; your Hands are Enfee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and your Enemies are Armed round about you. Do you not ſee your Common Enemies the <hi>Papists</hi> laugh aloud at your Separation? How thereby they ſeek to work your Deſtruction! They Love to ſet <hi>Ephraim</hi> againſt <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> againſt <hi>Ephraim.</hi> Call to mind the Times of old, have you forgot the Yoak of their Tyranny? Will you give the opportunity to theſe <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stines</hi> to Bind you and to take from you your Strength, by cutting away the Locks of Unity that would make you Invincible? Were you ever in more Danger than at this time? Do not you ſee them gnaſhing their Teeth at you round about? Methinks this preſſing neceſſity of Uniting ſhould now make you forget all Animoſities, and laying aſide all unneceſſary Cavils and Scruples, to joyn your Forces together leſt the <hi>Romans</hi> ſhould come. <hi>A Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand.</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude not your ſelves, you will be involved in the Ruine of your Brethren. The Church of <hi>England</hi> cannot ſuffer, but you will partake of her Sufferings alſo. Joyn therefore your Hands and your Stength together and become as one Nation; you will then daunt your Oppoſers, and Fruſtrate the hopes and deſigns of your Enemies. This Unity will be as a brazen Wall of Defence round about you, which they ſhall never be able to undermine or caſt down. Think of this preſſing neceſſity that at this time urges you to Conformity, leſt you fall into the worſt of Afflictions, to deſerve the Evils that will
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:66156:24"/>come upon you.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Boet. l.</hi> 1. <hi>Conſolat. Philoſ.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hoc tantum</hi> (ſays the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher) <hi>dixerim ultimam eſſe adverſae fortunae Sarci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, quod dum Miſeris aliquid crimen affigitur, quae praeferunt meruiſſe creduntur.</hi> Have a care, I ſay, that the blame be not juſtly fixed upon you, and that you deſerve not all thoſe Evils that you will bring upon your ſelves by this obſtinacy of not Conforming, and by this dangerous and pernicious Separation.</p>
            <p>Now is the time for you to look about you and to carry your Eyes in your Head, leſt <hi>Venient Romani</hi> become a Propheſie. See what you have got already by forſaking your Mother the Church of <hi>England,</hi> a Company of Spurious Brats that you would diſown, but are the Fruits of your Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. They have entred into the World by the ſame Gap that you firſt made, you have multiply'd your ſelves into Diviſions and Subdiviſions, and are become like the <hi>Phiſtines</hi> at <hi>Gibea,</hi> every <hi>Mans Sword againſt his Fellow.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.20.</note> Have a Care, I ſay, that Popery does not overrun us by your means. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Scandals and Advantages that you give to thoſe ſtrenuous Engins, they know how to Fiſh in our troubled Waters, and to get by our Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. There can be nothing more Beneficial to their Intentions, or that can Further their Deſigns more than to ſee us divided into ſo many Fracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and to ſtand lik Adverſaries ready to devour one another. They had no hopes ſo long as the happy Band of Unity remained unbroken; they know well the Maxim, <hi>Divide &amp; Impera,</hi> Divide and Raign. It has been all along their Policy to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:66156:24"/>cauſe Separation; they are a Cunning as well as a Malicious Generation, they are too Skilful for you in Politicks, their <hi>Jeſuites</hi> are bred Stateſmen, they are the <hi>Boutefeus</hi> of Kingdoms, they are in all places ready to ſet People and Nations together by the Ears; they make it their buſineſs to cauſe Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and to promote Separation. Their Spleen and Malice is againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> 'tis at her they only aim, ſhe is the mark of their Spite and Envy. They are a ſubtle ſort of People, they know you will ſoon periſh by her ruin, and that her fall muſt cruſh you to pieces. Therefore 'tis her Policy to make you like Vipers to gnaw aſunder the Womb of your Mother, and to eat your way to Separation thorow her bowels. See at laſt, I ſay, the Malice and Cunning of your Adverſaries, take example by your Enemies, learn of them to Unite for your own Security. What is it that makes the <hi>Roman</hi> Church yet ſo Potent in the World, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding her many Errors and more filthy Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions? 'Tis the Baſis of Unity; that very thing which they Inculcate as a Principle to all of her Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, <hi>Believe as the Church Believes,</hi> tyes them ſo ſtrictly together into one band that they cannot eaſily be broken. 'Tis this Unity which they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavor to maintain with all their Might and Force, which keeps them together and makes them ſo Strong. They are like the <hi>Grecian Phalanx</hi> not to be broken and therefore Invincible, or like the <hi>Roman</hi> Bands that lock'd one another faſt together with their Shields, as if they were all but one great Penthouſe againſt the falling Darts of their
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:66156:25"/>Enemies. They hinder therefore all Diſputes in their Religion that there may be no Diviſions. 'Tis the Strength of their Unity that makes them ſo Formidable; And as they know by that their own ſtrength, ſo they are ſenſible that nothing can more weaken their Adverſaries than to cauſe Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration among them. By this Policy they have done more miſchief than by their Arms, and when they cannot Convince by Argument nor Confound by Force, they this way overthrow by Cunning, by Policy, by Subtilty, making their Enemies do the Work for them; and by their breaking the Bands of Unity, Separate them one from another, and make them to become a Prey to them, who ſtand ready to make uſe of the Advantage; and like the Kite in the fable, carry away the feeble Comba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants pecking at one another with Bulruſhes and Bents.</p>
            <p>Are you not ſenſible that they are among you? That they are diſguiſed <hi>Papiſts, Jeſuists</hi> transform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the ſhapes of <hi>Presbyterians, Independents, Anabaptists, Quakers,</hi> that foment the Difference and Diſunion from the Church of <hi>England.</hi> They are very <hi>Proteus's,</hi> they can vary their Figures, they can feign Sanctity, and transform themſelves into Angels of Light. They are in your Pulpits, they can ſpeak your Words, they know how to Counterfiet your Voices, your Tones and your Dreſs. They become all things with all Men, in another fenſe than St. <hi>Paul</hi> meant. They do all this to promote their Cauſe, and which they are ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble they can no ways better do than by widening
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:66156:25"/>the breach of Separation, by keeping you aſunder and by increaſing your Diviſions. Open your Eyes at laſt and behold the ſubtilty of your inveterate Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, give them no longer this Advantage againſt you, hearken not to their wicked Sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions when they whiſper Rebellion into your Ears under the Notion of Liberty of Conſcience, and Diſobedience under the pretence of Sanctity and Holineſs; when they bid you not Submit and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form to the Rites and Ceremonies of the Church under the perſwaſion of your Purity: You have hearkned to them too long, at length know the Voyce of this <hi>Syren</hi> that Sings ſo melodiouſly in your Ears; 'twill at laſt draw you into the Sea of Perdition and Deſtruction, and betray you to more Miſeries than you have yet felt. I am Credibly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed they had the chief Hand in the late Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and that two of them ſuffered for it under the garb and ſhape of Holineſs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoring to promote the old Cauſe with a new Rebellion. Theſe are they that appear as harmleſs Doves, but are Ravenous Vultures; you take them to be harmleſs Sheep of your own flock, but they are Wolves that ſecretly devour you. They are ſubtle Foxes that ſecretly prey upon you, and are worſe than <hi>Samſon</hi>'s that had Fire-brands at their Tails.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.7.</note> They are like <hi>Ephraim</hi> they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the Ballances of Deceit in their Hands; they are cunning Merchants that know how to weigh your Tempers and Diſpoſitions.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.9.</note> They are the Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throat <hi>Hypocrites</hi> that deſtroy their Neighbours with their Mouths.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:66156:26"/>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pelliculam veterem retinent,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Perſ. Sat.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; fronte politi</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aſtutam vapido geſtant ſub pectore vulpem.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>Theſe are they that endeavour to keep you from Conformity, and with a thouſand cunning fetches and moſt ſpecious Pretences work you to their Wills, and never leave you till they have drawn you from Unity to Separation, from Separation to Rebellion, and ſo to Ruine and Deſtruction, and there they leave you.</p>
            <p>But if you will not believe all this, and ſhall think it feigned of them to affright and ſcare you, and that you cannot be made ſenſible of their cloſe and Hypocritical Intreagues; can you forget their unmask'd Cruelties? Their Horid Maſſacres? And Bloody Perſecutions? Do not you tremble leſt you ſhould fall anew under their Power? Are you not afraid more of their Tyrannical Yoke than of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting with your Brethren of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> Had you rather ſtoop to the Idolatrous Church of <hi>Rome</hi> than to your own Reformed Church? Will you rather admit again of all her Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions than a few Ceremonies in Ours? Would you be rather Content with the Bloody Court of the Inquiſition than with that of the Biſhops? Think yet of the Blood they have Spilt in this Kingdom in the time of their Raign, let the horror thereof a little move you, and let the fear of the like poſſeſs you with ſome thoughts of preventing it by your Unanimity and cloſing with your Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. Think a little of their Perſecutions and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:66156:26"/>Slaughters of the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> and <hi>Albigenſes</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> of the <hi>Huſſites</hi> in <hi>Bohemia,</hi> of the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> in <hi>Germany, Hungary,</hi> and the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> of the cruel Maſſacre in <hi>Paris,</hi> the horrid Deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and Cruelties of late years in <hi>Piedmont,</hi> the Bonfires of Martyrs in the days of Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> the Gunpowder Plot, and our late Wars begun and fomented by them and their Agents abroad and at home. They are ſtill the ſame Sedulous promoters of their own Cauſe; they are no Changelings. Are your Eyes ſtill ſhut? Have you not ſeen your dear City conſumed to Aſhes by their Fire Balls? And do not you now behold new Plots and Contrivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, by the ſame Perſons, to ruine the Church, the State and the Kingdom? Have we not ſeen a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of Juſtice Murthered by their Hands? Are not we daily threatned with farther Miſchief? And if not prevented by the over-ruling hand of Divine Providence, and by the Care of our Prince and his Faithful Counſellors, are we not ſtill in danger? What gives them this Advantage againſt us but your Separation? What makes their hopes Flouriſh but your Diviſion? At laſt therefore harken, I beſeech you, to the Call of your Brethren, who ſtill invite you to Unity and Conformity; that <hi>the Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>and the Children of</hi> Judah <hi>may come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and ſeek their Lord their God:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 50.4, 5.</note> That <hi>they may joyn themſelves to the Lord in a perpetual Covenant that ſhall not be forgotten.</hi> That you may become as one People and that your Breaches may be made up. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:66156:27"/>
            <p>If you are not Men of a perverſe Nature, if you have not Hearts of <hi>Adamant</hi> that cannot be pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, if you will not Conſider the Good of the Kingdom nor your own Danger; yet if you have any Souls or any ſpark of Generoſity or good Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in your Breaſts, methinks the Kindneſs, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Indulgence of the King ſhown towards you ſhould draw you to a Compliance. Hearts that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Tortures nor Racks could overcome, Souls irreſiſtible to Force, not to be Conquered by Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, have yet melted before the Fire of Love, have been overcome with Kindneſs, have acknowledged and ſubmitted to Generoſity. Flints are eaſily bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken on beds of Down, Adamants are made ſoft by the blood of Goats. And is there no way to penetrate your rocky Hearts? Will not Indulgence move you? Nor Kindneſs draw you? Nor Mercy allure you? Nor Favor cauſe you? Nor Good-Will invite you to Conform? Will neither fair means nor foul work upon you? Could you ever have hop'd for or expected the great Favor and Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence that hath been ſhown you by your Prince, one that is juſtly ſtyl'd the Merciful, after all thoſe Evils that you had brought upon this Nation by your Separation from and Oppoſition to the Church? Has he not moderated the Laws made againſt you? Has he not hindred all Force to be uſed towards you? Has he not ſuffered you to injoy your darling private Meetings in Contempt of the Church, and in the Face of the whole Nation? Are you Moleſted and Diſturbed? Would you have granted the ſame Toleration, had you had the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:66156:27"/>Power in your Hand? We Know and Remember the time that you would not, and we yet are in doubt of your good will in that Caſe, had you the Reins in your Hands. You ſay, you acknowledg it, you own the Mercy and great Favor and Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, therefore you Pray for the King, and wiſh Life to his Majeſty for your own Ends; but ſtill Diſobey him and his Laws by your ſtubborn reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the kind Invitations given you to Unity and Conformity. Let at laſt the great Mercy that is ſhown you be a Motive to bring you to this deſired and happy Unity. Let Love draw you, reſiſt no longer, meet with kindneſs and ſubmiſſion the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevolence and tender Heartedneſs of ſo Gracious a Prince towards you. Return like the loſt Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Son to the Father of your Country, and into the Boſom of your Mother, that the fatted Calf may be killed and that there may be a general re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing and Jubilee throughout the Land. Then ſhall we ſay, <hi>Sing O ye Heavens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.23.</note> 
               <hi>for the Lord hath done it: ſhout ye lower parts of the Earth: break forth into Singing ye Mountains, O Forreſt and every Tree therein: for the Lord hath redeemed</hi> Jacob, <hi>and glorified himſelf in</hi> Iſrael.</p>
            <p>Though I have already mentioned your Duty to the Magiſtrate, that you ought to ſubmit to and obey your Prince and your Governors, that your juſt Obedience to Authority is Required and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by Scripture, and againſt which you can have no lawful Defence; I cannot but again remind you of this neceſſary Duty, how will you Anſwer this before God? After what manner can you
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:66156:28"/>evade ſuch poſitive Commands? The Infidelity of Princes could not excuſe this Law: How then can you Anſwer your Contempt of the Laws and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands not only of a Chriſtian but a Proteſtant Prince? One that Commands nothing but Lawful things: It is not enough that you think otherwiſe of them, and that you pretend ſcruples of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, there is no ſuch exception in the Rule laid down by the Apoſtle.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.22, 23</note> 
               <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher Powers. Submit to every Ordinance of Man. Hath the Lord as great delight in Burnt-offerings and Sacrifices as in obeying the voice of the Lord? To obey is better than Sacrifice: and to harken than the fat of Rams. Rebellion is as the Sin of Witchcraft: and Stubbornneſs is as Iniquity and Idolatry.</hi> Certainly obedience to your Prince and to his Lawful Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands would be more acceptable than all your long Prayers and frequent Preaching which is become your Idol, and which you ſet up in the room of the Croſſes you have pull'd down. Speak out and tell us whether an Act for Uniformity and Conformity made by the three States of the Land be a Legal Act or no, if it be, why do you not obey? Why do you trouble the Waters with your needleſs Scruples of little weight and value, and about trifles only as you Call them? Is not the Word truly diſpenſed in the Publick Churches? Are not the Sacraments rightly Adminiſtred? Are not their Prayers free from Scandal or Irreverence? Are not their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines clear of Error or Falſity? Why then do you deny to Hear, Receive and Communicate together? But in ſpite (as I may ſay) both of the Commands
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:66156:28"/>of God and Man, Separate your ſelves and run into Diſobedience? I verily believe thoſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> would never run into that Contempt of the King and his Laws; I am perſwaded that for Conſcience ſake they would ſubmit, ſhould the King and Parliament by their Authority take away thoſe Ceremonies about which you Contend. They have learnt better than to Rebel, and the Doctrine of of their Church hath imbued them with ſounder and better Principles. But God forbid that to gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie thoſe who can ſhow no ſound Reaſon for what they would have, no lawful or weighty plea for what they do, and can pretend nothing but a ſtubborn Will and refractory Conſcience, that the decent Garments of the Church ſhould be curtail'd or taken from her, or that ſhe ſhould loſe the leaſt ſhred thereof. But have you forgot already how ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently you preſſed Obedience from your Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits? And theſe very Texts now ſhown you were in all your Mouths when you would have ſet up your own Sanctified Form, to bring the People to your Lure and to ſubmit to your Rule. If they were then the Commands of God and ought to be obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, how comes it that they are not ſo ſtill? Or do the Biſhops Command worſe things than <hi>Goodwyn, Manton</hi> or <hi>Nye?</hi> Is ſubmiſſion to theſe Lawful, to thoſe not? Does not the fifth Commandment, <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor your Father,</hi> reach to your King the Father of his Country?
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Icon Baſ. p.</hi> 285.</note> Or to the Biſhops the Fathers of the Church? The Royal Martyr obſerves, that you had not Loyalty enough to ſay Amen to thoſe Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for his Majeſty which are in the Common
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:66156:29"/>Prayer, and that he believed it was one of the greateſt faults ſome Men could find in it. What ſignifies it to Command if there be no Obedience? There ought to be an Harmony betwixt Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Obeying, they ſhould go Hand in Hand: they are both Arts or rather make up but one Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, for one cannot be well without the other. King cannot be well without Subjects nor Subjects without one to Command.
<note place="margin">Eraſ.</note> 
               <hi>Imperare, &amp; parere im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perio, Ars emnium pulcherrima: quae duae res a Civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus excludunt ſeditiones, &amp; tuentur Concordiam.</hi> They are Correlatives and make up but one fair Art, but 'tis theſe two that maintain Concord, Amity and Peace, and ſhut out Seditions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions. For your Kings ſake, for the ſake of the Laws, and for your Countries ſake,
<q>— <hi>Amor Patriae ratione valentior omni,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ovid. de Pont.</note>
               </q> which ſhould be of more Power to perſwade you than any Argument I could bring. Harken at laſt to good Counſel and be longer Obſtinate, do not provoke Clemency it ſelf to Anger, and Mercy to Juſtice.
<q>
                  <hi>Frangendum est,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Mo. Viat.</note> 
                  <hi>quod nulla Caput Clementia Mollit.</hi>
               </q> If nothing will mollifie you, may you not expect to be broken? Outlying Deer are to be frightned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Pale for their own ſecurity.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.8, 5.</note> 
               <hi>Harden not your Hearts to day if you will hear his Voice,</hi> let it be inſtantly, accept of the proffered kindneſs, defer it
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:66156:29"/>no longer, put it not off till to morrow,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Prov.</hi> 27.1.</note> 
               <hi>For you know not what a day may bring forth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now after all this what ſhould I ſay more to urge and perſwade you to Conformity? I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready told you the danger we are in by theſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions cauſed by your Diſunion, and the Evil that ſeems to hang over our Heads threatning us with the ſtormy cloud of Popery. Fire and Fagot ſeem to be enkindling in our Streets by your diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, new Plots to embroyl a Nation are incouraged by your Nonconformity; and a great Gap is made whereby our preſent Adverſaries are ready to enter and to overturn the Fabrick of our Church by your Breach. Behold all this I beſeech you with an Eye of Pity and Commiſeration, and ſtand no longer on Scruples and Niceties. Be not affrighted at <hi>Mormoes</hi> of your own making; yield at laſt to neceſſity and involve not all in ruin by your obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy. Leave all By-reſpects and Self-intereſt, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine your Conſciences and deal nakedly with your own Souls, and tell us truly if you do not think an Unity betwixt you and your Brethren would not be an happineſs to this Nation: You cannot but Know it and Confeſs it ſecretly: Lay aſide then your Terms, ſtand not ſo ſtifly upon Capitulations; acknowledge that 'tis as Lawful for Biſhops to Rule as for the Superintendents in the <hi>Lutheran</hi> Churches or leading Presbyters in <hi>Geneva.</hi> Boggle no longer at Words; ſtartle not at Titles. Lords, Maſters, Fathers, are Scriptural phraſes and given to good and holy Men. They are Terms not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitting and avowable. But are theſe things to be
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:66156:30"/>ſtood upon now? Are they of value to Continue the Breach betwixt you? Ought there to be this difference about Indifferent things? Is it not better to take St.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.3.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi>'s Counſel to the <hi>Romans. Let not him that eateth deſpiſe him that eateth not: and let not him that eateth not, judge him that eateth.</hi> He tells them this, that although there were ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate difference among them in indifferent matters, yet that they ſhould Continue in their Unity and not make any Separation betwixt each other, but labour in the Edification and Inſtruction of each other,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 1.</note> though one be weak and the other be ſtrong, though ſome have ſcruples of ſmall weight and others know better things,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.1.</note> and not by break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the band of their Unity and Community ſeek to ruine each other. Let not thoſe that Conform deſpiſe the weakneſs of thoſe who do Not, nor let thoſe who do not Conform judge the Liberty of thoſe that Do. They that break this Rule want Charity, and this ought to be exerciſed on both ſides where Indifferent things are not determined and made otherways by Authority. That alters the Caſe, for though they are ſtill the ſame in their Natures, that is Indifferent; yet they are not ſo in their uſe, becauſe enjoyned. Thoſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> do not deſpiſe you for your ſcruples, for they would receive you; and they intrude not her Conſtitutions as the Laws of God but as the Laws of Men, not of Divine neceſſity but of humane In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution for the more orderly Worſhip of God, and that there might be a general Uniformity in the Church. Shew therefore by your Conformity, ſince
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:66156:30"/>you are thereto Lawfully required, that you do not judge your Brother as he doth not deſpiſe you, but that you will live in Charity and Unity as you ought to do. Be not any longer ſo Scrupulous, nay I may ſay Superſtitious;
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sand. Serm. ad Clerum</hi> 4 <hi>Sect.</hi> 11.</note> for as Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> ſays, <hi>The taking away of Indifferency from Indifferent things is in Truth Superſtition: either by requiring them as Neceſſary or forbidding them as <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful.</hi> Let the leſſer obligation give way to the greater. For if Opinion may make a good thing Evil to him that doubts or thinks it Evil,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23.</note> 
               <hi>for what is not of Faith is Sin,</hi> it cannot however make a thing Evil in it ſelf to become either good in it ſelf or ſo to him that thinks ſo. To diſobey the Commands of Authority is of it ſelf a very great Evil, and your Opinion that you may Separate and not Conform can never make it Good to you notwithſtanding your ſcruples, nor can any ways Juſtifie your Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, becauſe Diſobedience is of it ſelf a great Evil. Now our Governors or thoſe in Authority over us have Commanded thoſe things to be done about which you ſcruple, and that by the Authority of the Scripture,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.40.</note> 
               <hi>Let all things be done decently and in Order,</hi> which gives them a Power to make ſuch Conſtitutions; therefore all your ſcruples of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience cannot take off the greater Obligation of Obedience which you are expreſly bound to in Conſcience by Gods Command, and you are no longer <hi>ſui juris,</hi> where a Superior Power has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined your Liberty. If you ſcruple to play at Cards and Dice or any other indifferent thing of which you have Power to determine to do or not
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:66156:31"/>to do, if you do it againſt your Conſcience you ſin, becauſe you are <hi>ſui juris</hi> in that Caſe, there being no Obligation upon you to the Contrary; but if you ſcruple coming to Church becauſe of the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, being both a good Action and Commanded by Authority, not to do it muſt certainly be a great Sin, notwithſtanding your ſcruples to the contrary, for you are not at your own choice but under Obedience; and thereby bound in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence as if God had Commanded them himſelf, for he hath given you his ſtrict Command <hi>to obey the higher Powers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>and to ſubmit to their Ordinances;</hi> neither will it avail you to plead your ſcruples of Conſcience,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5.</note> ſince you are Commanded <hi>to obey for Conſcience ſake,</hi> and ſince what is Commanded is no Sin: For if the Magiſtrate ſhould Command us to take Gods Name in vain or to Commit Fornication, we may with a ſafe Conſcience diſobey, becauſe we have an higher Obligation upon us, for that God has Commanded the Contrary and we are bound to obey God before Man. Be at laſt Convinced and ſtand no longer upon theſe niceties and ſcruples about things of leſſer weight when greater Dangers are impending, and much trouble is ready to ariſe by reaſon of this Separation and Diſunion between you:
<note place="margin">Saluſt.</note> have a care that by your diſcord you do not ruin your ſelves. <hi>Diſcordia maximae Res dilabuntur:</hi> it is able to overthrow Kingdoms, give the Hag no longer entertainment among you; let her be baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from our Churches as well as from our Kingdom, that at laſt we may meet with oneneſs of Heart and ſingleneſs of Mind as becometh Brethren.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22.3.8.</note> 
               <hi>Love one
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:66156:31"/>another with a pure Heart fervently: Be ye all of one Mind, having Compaſſion one of another: Love as Brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whatſoever the pretences of many are, yet we find that Intereſt ſways more with them than Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: very few do refrain purely for Conſcience ſake. Many do it becauſe they have been bred ſo, and will not or care not to be better inform'd: moſt remain Nonconformiſts without being able to ſhew any tolerable Reaſon why they are ſo, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides thoſe Idle Opinions they have of the Impurity of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Methinks theſe ſort of People who ſhun the Church out of a certain ſquea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhneſs of her nearneſs (as they falſly think) to Popery, ſhould be afraid of thoſe viſible advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages their Separation gives to thoſe of that Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to contrive its ſetting up again in this Land, and that this fear ſhould let them ſee that it is their Common intereſt to Unite with and ſtrengthen the Hands of their Brethren. Certainly though you intend no ſuch thing, yet you are a means of the great increaſe of <hi>Popery</hi> in this Land by your Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions. How would that Party rejoyce could they ſee Epiſcopacy as it is now Eſtabliſhed in this Land pulled down, they would not much care what Form you would ſet up, for they believe, and not amiſs, that Confuſions and Diſtractions would ſoon follow, on which they ground their not improbable Hopes of Raiſing up their own Church upon our broken Pillars. You cry out continually, with no little noiſe of the growth and increaſe of Popery or of People perverted to Popery in this Land, but
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:66156:32"/>look not on your ſelves as the Means and Cauſe by your Separation, giving them the ſame pretence for that plea of yours, Liberty of Conſcience, and that they ought not to be compelled any more than your ſelves.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 6.31.</note> 
               <hi>Do as you would be done unto.</hi> If you would not be compelled why ſhould they? <hi>Prout vultis ut faciant vobis homines, vos etiam facite eis ſimiliter.</hi> What reaſon have you to lay any force upon others when you will not have any laid upon your ſelves? The Common Intereſt could make <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> though Enemies to become Friends for fear of a Common Enemy the King of the Jews. See I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you now if it be not your Intereſt to cloſe with thoſe of the Church of <hi>England</hi> againſt your Common Enemy of <hi>Rome,</hi> and if it be not now moſt ſeaſonable to effect it. This Union would be the beſt means in the World to fruſtrate all their Plots and Deſigns againſt us. It would put them quite out of Heart, and daſh all their Hopes. They would then loſe their ſheet Anchor their laſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge: It would take away all their Advantages and put them paſt all their ſhifts: It is the only way to bring Peace and Happineſs to the Nation. We need to fear no Enemies abroad if we were thus United at home: we ſhould be like the bundle of Arrows not to be broken together, but being par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted aſunder into Factions eaſily broke into pieces. Union is the Life and Blood of Government both in the Church as well as in the State. A <hi>Doeg</hi> or <hi>Achitophel</hi> at home is worſe than the <hi>Philistines</hi> or <hi>Moabites</hi> abroad. Our miſchief is from our ſelves.
<note place="margin">Eraſ. Apoth.</note> 
               <hi>Patriae periclitantis potius habenda eſt ratio
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:66156:32"/>quam privatae incolumitatis.</hi> We ſhould rather re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the ſafety of our Country than of our ſelves. <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaid their was a ſelect place of Happineſs and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal felicity reſerved in Heaven for thoſe who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, helpt, and brought good to their Country.
<note place="margin">Som. Scip.</note> And I am of the Opinion that by your Conformity you will merit more than by all your ſcruples of Separation. By your ſubmiſſion you will deſerve the Reward of Victors; you ſhall have the Garland of Praiſe to adorn your Brows; the Palm of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt ſhall be put into your Hands; and the Olive Branch of Peace ſhall be placed on your Trophies; your Country ſhall applaud you, your King ſhall cheriſh you, and your Brethren ſhall rejoyce with you; you ſhall have the right hand of fellowſhip given to you, and there ſhall be no longer any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in our <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cic. Off. l.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Pro patria quis bonus dubitet mortem oppetere?</hi> What good Man doubts to meet Death for his Countries ſake? ſays <hi>Cicero.</hi> The task is not ſo difficult that is required of you; you are deſired to Live for your Countries ſake, to Live in Union and Love with your Friends, and to joyn to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againſt your Common Foes. It is not enough that you ſay you will joyn your Purſes and your Arms with your Brethren, and that you are ready to aſſiſt them with your Lives and Fortunes: for where there is not a Unity of Hearts and Religion there can be no true Concord and Amity. There will ſtill remain jealouſies and ſuſpicions among you. There can be no perfect Confidence and truſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween you. There will be a thouſand fears and doubts of each other; diſtruſts and ſurmiſes will
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:66156:33"/>ſtill ariſe till you are United in Heart and in Mind, and remain no longer two but one.</p>
            <p>O that I could but make you ſenſible of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of this Unity; how much Glory it would add to the Nation! How much ſcandal it would take from Religion! How much ſecurity it would give to three Kingdoms! How much content and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to your Prince, and how much joy and gladneſs to the Hearts of all your Brethren: what Peace ſhould we injoy at home! What eſteem and aw ſhould we purchaſe abroad! What Love would be begotten between one another! And what hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs and proſperity would it bring to all! You would then ſee again thoſe Happy days of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> our Armies to Proſper, our Citizens to Flouriſh; Conqueſt abroad and Peace at home; Charity to increaſe and Contention to ceaſe; Love to abound and Strife to wax leſs.
<q>— <hi>redeunt Saturnia Regna.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Virg.</note>
               </q> The golden Age would ſeem to be returned again, and Righteouſneſs would run down like a ſtream. There would then be a general rejoycing in our Streets,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.23</note> and we ſhould all Cry out, <hi>This is the Lords doing: it is marvellous in our Eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If I thought I were able to prevail with you, I could be willing to ſpend my Breath in Calling; but how often have you been Call'd unto and ye will not hear! How often have you been Cry'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and you are ſtill Deaf! The King has Call'd you, the Laws have Call'd you, your Fathers and your
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:66156:33"/>Brethren have Call'd you and Cry'd aloud unto you, and yet you will not hear, you will not Anſwer as you ought, you will and do ſtill contend and ſtill ſtand out; you do ſubmit you ſay to the Laws, you are peaceable and quiet; you diſturb not the Church, you Aſſemble your ſelves only to hear the Word and to ſatisfie your Conſcience; you Pray for the King, you Preach and Hear ſound Doctrine, Why then ſhould we diſturb you by theſe frequent Callings? 'Tis true you do Obey the Laws, but 'tis by halves; 'tis a paſſive obedience only; you ſtep not one ſtep forward; you ſtand ſtill and ſuffer as as you think; you thereby judge your ſelves no leſs than Martyrs and Sufferers for your Cauſe and for your Conſcience; you reſiſt not becauſe your Hands are bound, but you ſtill Watch and Wait and Pray for a day of Deliverance; you Hope ſtill to have your turn, and you are ſtill Righteous in your own Eyes: you Pray for the King, 'tis your Duty, and he hath deſerv'd it by his Indulgence; you Preach ſound Doctrine, that is alſo to be heard in our Pulpits; but Obedience is better than all this, Unity and Conformity would be of more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to you, and, doubt not, more acceptable to God than all your Prayers, than all your Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing joyned with Diſobedience. At laſt therefore indeavour to ſatisfie your Conſciences, go about it in earneſt, lay aſide all ſtubbornneſs of Heart, all Spiritual Pride, all Self-intereſt. Let the Caſe be ſtated truly betwixt you: There are thoſe that will not think much to convince you if Scripture and Reaſon will do it. But you muſt then Come with
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:66156:34"/>willing Minds, you muſt not be ſo ſtiff as you have hitherto been, rather than comply one jot you will break, you cannot bow; you will not yield in what you may, in thoſe things that you cannot Condemn; you will not ſo much as Read the Chapters appointed for the Day, becauſe Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; you will not repeat the Creed and the ten Commandments; you will but rarely admit of the Lords Prayer, becauſe by us ſo often uſed, and thoſe who have thus far Complied and ſet you a good Example have been reproach'd for it, and have been look'd upon as backſliders. But this is not the way to Unity and Peace, you muſt bring willing and yielding Hearts with you; you muſt not be Obſtinate and Opiniative; you muſt not be Reſolved before Hand; you muſt have deſires and longings for Unity; you muſt hear without Paſſion and Intereſt, and with a deſire not of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting and ſhewing your Parts but of ſatisfying your Minds and Conſciences, and then no doubt but your ſcruples may be all Reſolved, and you may Conform with ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>Lay theſe things ſeriouſly to your Heart, paſs them not ſlightly over, think not theſe words only a little vain Air, God may Call you by a weak In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument, by a ſmall Voice. <hi>Reſiſt not the Spirit, Harden not your Hearts.</hi> 'Tis God that Calls, he would have you return, <hi>Remember the Womb wherein you were born, and the Paps that gave you ſuck.</hi> Think of the Peace and Unity of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Be Dutiful as Children. Love as Brethren. Obey the King. Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to Ordinances. Be Subject to Rulers. Honour
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:66156:34"/>the Magiſtrate. Yield to Governors. Be United in Mind. Be of one Heart. Worſhip together. Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate no longer, and God will build you up.
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 76.1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>Then God will be known in</hi> Judah, <hi>and his Name will be great in</hi> Iſrael. <hi>In</hi> Salem <hi>ſhall be his Tabernacle, and his Name ſhall be great in</hi> Zion. <hi>You ſhall then be <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted like</hi> Iſrael <hi>and</hi> Judah, <hi>you ſhall have but one King, you ſhall be no more two Nations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eze.</hi> 37.22.</note> 
               <hi>neither ſhall you be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into two Kingdoms any more at all. Then what Nation will there be ſo Great, who hath God ſo nigh unto them? Then you ſhall be his People,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.7.</note> 
               <hi>and He will be your God. He will give you one Heart, and one Way, that you may fear him for ever;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 32.38, 39 <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.6.</note> 
               <hi>for the good of you and your Children after you. Then will ye with one Mind, and one Voice glorifie God, even the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. For ye were as Sheep going aſtray, but are now returned unto the Shepherd and Biſhop of our Souls.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.25.</note> 
               <hi>Then there ſhall be but one Shepherd and one Fold, and they ſhall hear his Voice together. Then ſhall ye all be glad in the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>the Righteous ſhall rejoyce,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.11.</note> 
               <hi>and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright in Heart ſhall ſhout for Joy. Then ſhall you have Beauty for Aſhes, the Oil of Joy for Mourning, and the Garment of Praiſe for Heavineſs, and the Lord ſhall be Glorified.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.3.</note> 
               <hi>Therefore Remember from whence you are fallen and Repent.</hi> Return into the Boſom of your Mother,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.2.</note> 
               <hi>That your Joy may be compleat in the Lord,</hi> and that there may be ſeen throughout the Land, <hi>all to be like Minded, having one and the ſame Love, being of one accord, and of one Mind.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <pb n="66" facs="tcp:66156:35"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Inobedientia eſt ex duritia mentis obſtinatae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tullius.</note> 
               <hi>cui de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beas, imperanti nolle obtemperare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tres ſunt ſpecies obſtinatorum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hug. de</hi> 12. <hi>abuſi.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Prima eorum qui Correctione non Proficiunt. Secunda eorum qui ex Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitione deteriores fiunt. Tertia eorum qui emendatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem promittunt ſed non faciunt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pleniſſima Peccatorum obtinetur ablutio,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leo Papa Serm.</note> 
               <hi>quando to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius Eccleſiae una eſt Oratio, &amp; una Confeſſio. Si enim duorum vel trium Sanctiorum pio Conſenſui omnia, quae popoſcerint Dominus praeſtanda promittit, quid negabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur multorum millium Plebi unam obſervantiam pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter exequenti, &amp; per unum Spiritum concorditer ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicanti?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cujus aures Clauſi Veritati ſunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tul. de amic.</note> 
               <hi>ut ab amico verum audire nequeat, hujus ſalus deſperanda est.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:66156:35"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
